<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!-- Copyright (C) 2000 Brian Duff / Dubh.org -->

<projectlist>

  <project name="NewsAgent" href="newsagent/index.xml">
    <description>
      <p>
        NewsAgent is a USENET Newsreader written completely in Java. It was
        originally my final year project at University, but I later released
        it as open source and have been working on it on and off for two 
        years.
      </p>
    </description>
  </project>
  
  <project name="Java Utilities" href="dju/index.xml">
    <description>
      <p>
        While developing <a href="newsagent/index.xml">NewsAgent</a>, I had
        some vague general feeling that keeping stuff which might possibly
        come in useful for other projects in the future separate from the
        NewsAgent source code would be a good idea. This general code is
        DJU (the Dubh Java Utilities).
      </p>
      <p>
        DJU contains a number of useful classes for internationalization, 
        and funky UI widgets using Swing. The code is really due for a big
        tidyup any time soon.
      </p>
    </description>
  </project>
  
  <project name="Mail Providers" href="dmp/index.xml">
    <description>
      <p>
        <a href="http://www.sun.com">Sun</a> didn't announce JavaMail until
        well after I had finished the first version of NewsAgent. When JavaMail
        came along, it seemed like a good idea to try to migrate the hyper
        dodgy networking code in NewsAgent into a nice generic NNTP provider
        for JavaMail. This took a little longer than I expected, though :)
      </p>
    </description>
  </project>
  
  <project name="JFreeCiv" href="jfreeciv/index.xml">
    <description>
      <p>
        I'm completely addicted to strategy games of any kind. But in
        particular, I've been playing Civilization in various forms since
        it first came out on the Atari ST many years ago. 
      </p>
      <p>
        <a href="http://www.freeciv.org">FreeCIV</a> is an open source effort
        to write a replica of Civilization II. Unfortunately it's in C, and I
        don't really like C much. ..name goes here.. wrote a Java version, and
        I'm currently maintaining it...
      </p>
    </description>
  </project>
  
  <project name="Dev Tools" href="buildtools/index.xml">
    <description>
      <p>
        It can be a bit of a pain to build all these projects using disparate
        build systems. Javac is great, but it's just a compiler. To get cool
        automated build systems running or distribute scripts that build your
        project with the code can sometimes involve writing makefiles or batch/
        shell scripts.
      </p>
      <p>
        Someone pointed me in the direction of the Apache Jakarta Ant project,
        just as I was really getting into XML properly. This neatly solved most
        of my problems. The really nice thing was, I could solve all the other
        problems, because the authors of Ant made it really easy to hook into.
        Hence, Dubh Dev Tools are a bunch of "Task"s for Ant, as well as some
        other useful stuff for building the projects on this site.
      </p>
    </description>
  </project>
  
  <project name="EWatcher" href="ewatcher/index.xml">
    <description>
      <p>
        EWatcher is an attempt to define a Java framework for push technology.
        My original idea was that I'd like to have a ticker-tape-esque application
        running on my desktop, which was capable of receiving events from a number
        of sources (e.g. email with a certain subject / sender, updates to web
        pages, clock events, file changes on the network etc.) and displaying
        these prioritized in the ticker.
      </p>
    </description>
  </project>
  
  <project name="JDav" href="jdav/index.xml">
    <description>
      <p>
        Something I'm doing at work involves <a href="http://www.webdav.org">
        WebDAV</a>, so I did a little research into it. Then in a furious few 
        hours coding, I wrote a Java client API for accessing WebDAV resources
        in a convenient way. I did this at home, rather than at work, so it's
        all open source, and I'll probably develop it further.
      </p>
    </description>
  </project>


</projectlist>