<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/xsl/dubhpage.xsl" ?>

<!-- Copyright (C) 2000, 2001 Brian Duff / Dubh.Org -->


<dubhpage xmlns:xsql="urn:oracle-xsql">
  
  <title>Project Marco: Draft Requirements</title>
  
  <navigator>
    <xsql:include-xsql href="../../../navigator.xml?me=marco" />
  </navigator>  
  
  <content>
    <h1>Project Marco: Draft Requirements</h1>
    
    <h2>Abstract</h2>
    
    <p>
      This document is a draft set of requirements for the Marco project.
    </p>
    
    <h2>Goals</h2>
    
    <p>
      Marco has the following goals:
    </p>
    
    <ul>
      <li>Provide a hosted bookmark service</li>
      <li>Provide access for multiple users</li>
      <li>Work using the latest technologies</li>
    </ul>
    
    
    
    <h2>Requirements</h2>
    
    <h3 class="must">1. Must Allow Bookmarks to be Viewed Over the Web</h3>
    
    <p>
      The service must allow bookmarks to be viewed on a web page in a format
      that is convenient.
    </p>
    
    <div class="indent" >
      
      <h3 class="must">1.1 Must Display Bookmarks for an Individual User</h3>
      
      <p>
        For each user, there are a set of bookmarks. The main way to view
        bookmarks will be to show all the bookmarks for a particular user.
      </p>
      
      <div class="indent">
        <h3 class="could">1.1.1 Could Allow Users to View Other User's Bookmarks</h3>
        
        <p>
          Used in combination with a "publishing" scheme - see requirement
          x.x below.
        </p>
      </div>
      
      
      <h3 class="must">1.2 Must Display Bookmarks by Title</h3>
      
      <p>
        The natural way to represent bookmarks is using a symbolic title
        provided by the user.
      </p>
      
      <h3 class="must">1.3 Must Allow Each Bookmark to Jump to a URL</h3>
      
      <p>
        Bookmarks also consist of a URL. No two bookmarks with the same URL
        can exist. The URL identifies the target location of the bookmark.
      </p>
      
      <h3 class="must">1.4 Must Group Bookmarks Into Categories</h3>
      
      <p>
        Most web browsers which store bookmarks store them in nested
        categories, which makes it easier to locate bookmarks.
      </p>
      
      <div class="indent">
      
        <h3 class="must">1.4.1 Must Allow View to be Restricted to a Subset of Categories</h3>
        
        <p>
          Displaying all bookmarks in all categories all the time will make it
          difficult to locate bookmarks, even if you have an idea which
          category it is in.
        </p>
        
        <h3 class="should">1.4.2 Should Allow Bookmarks to Appear in More Than One Category</h3>
        
        <p>
          Sometimes it is convenient to put a bookmark in two or more
          different categories.
        </p>
        
        <h3 class="should">1.4.3 Should Display Uncategorized Bookmarks</h3>
        
        <p>
          The user may choose to categorize bookmarks at a later date.
        </p>
      
      </div>
      
      
    </div>
    
    <h3 class="must">2. Must Allow Bookmarks to be Edited Over the Web</h3>
    
    <div class="indent">
      
      <h3 class="must">2.1 Must Provide User-Level Authentication</h3>
      
      <p>
        It's essential that the service prevents users from modifying
        bookmarks for which they do not have authorization.
      </p>
      
      <h3 class="must">2.2 Must Allow Bookmarks to be Edited</h3>
      
      <div class="indent">
        <h3 class="must">2.2.1 Must Allow A Bookmark to be Renamed</h3>
        
        <h3 class="must">2.2.2 Must Allow the URL of A Bookmark to be Changed</h3>
        
        <h3 class="must">2.2.3 Must Allow A Bookmark to be Re-ordered in Its Category</h3>
        
        <h3 class="must">2.2.4 Must Allow A Bookmark to be Moved to a Different Category</h3>
        
        <h3 class="must">2.2.5 Must Allow A Bookmark to be Deleted</h3>
        
        <h3 class="should">2.2.6 Should Allow A Bookmark to be Uncategorized</h3>
      </div>
      
      <h3 class="must">2.3 Must Allow Categories to be Edited</h3>
      
      <div class="indent">
        <h3 class="must">2.3.1 Must Allow A Category to be Renamed</h3>
        
        <h3 class="must">2.3.2 Must Allow A Category to be Deleted</h3>
        
        <h3 class="must">2.3.3 Must Allow A Category to be Re-ordered in Its Parent Category</h3>
        
        <h3 class="should">2.3.4 Should Allow A Category to be Reparented</h3>
        
        <p>
          Categories are hierarchical. It should be possible to move categories
          about in the hierarchy.
        </p>
        
        <h3 class="could">2.3.5 Could Allow Categories to be Published</h3>
      
        <p>
          Publishing a category would allow other users to see all bookmarks
          and published subcategories.
        </p>

      </div>
      
    </div>
    
    <h3 class="must">3. Must Allow User to Administer Their Account Over the Web</h3>
    
    <div class="indent">
      
      <h3 class="must">3.1 Must Allow a User to Create a New Account</h3>
      
      <p>
        Each user is identified by their account on the service. New users
        should be able to create an account. An account consists of an
        email address, name and password.
      </p>
      
      <h3 class="must">3.2 Must Allow a User to Change the Email Address of Their Account</h3>
      
      <h3 class="must">3.3 Must Allow a User to Change the Password of Their Account</h3>
      
      <h3 class="must">3.4 Must Allow a User to Change the Name of Their Account</h3>
      
      <h3 class="must">3.5 Must Allow a User to Close Their Account</h3>
      
      <h3 class="should">3.6 Should Allow a User to Mail a Password, Given an Email Address</h3>
      
      <p>
        This is a common way of reminding users what their password is.
      </p>
      
    </div>
    
    
    <h3 class="should">4. Should Provide Web-Based Administrative Control Over the Service</h3>
    
      <div class="indent">
      <h3 class="should">4.1 Should Allow User Accounts to Be Administered</h3>
      
      <p>
        All functionality listed under requirement 3 should be available to
        the administrator for any account on the service.
      </p>
      
      </div>
    
    <h3 class="should">5. Should Allow Bookmarks to be Retrieved in XML Format</h3>
    
    <p>
      Providing access to bookmarks in XML allows easier application
      interoperability. For instance, an XML bookmarks document could be 
      transformed using XSLT into RDF, or into XUI for embedding in Mozilla.
    </p>
    
    <h3 class="should">6. Should Allow Bookmarks to be Queried and Modified 
      Programatically</h3>
    
    <p>
      Again, for application interoperability, it would be nice if the bookmarks 
      service could be controlled and queried programatically. This should be
      as language-neutral as possible, for instance, as a SOAP web service.
    </p>
    
  </content>
  
</dubhpage>
