<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/xsl/dubhpage.xsl" ?>

<!-- Copyright (C) 2000, 2001 Brian Duff / Dubh.Org -->


<dubhpage xmlns:xsql="urn:oracle-xsql">
  
  <title>Dubh.Org: About</title>
  
  <navigator>
    <xsql:include-xsql href="../navigator.xml?me=about" />
  </navigator>  
  
  <content type="mixed">
    <html>
    <h1>About Dubh.Org</h1>

    <h2>What is Dubh.Org?</h2>

      <p>
        Dubh.Org is a web server which is mostly dedicated to
        the development and support of several open source <a
        href="../projects/index.xml">projects</a> and other assorted
        technologies.
      </p>
      <p>
        The server is maintained by <a href="../brian/index.xml">
        Brian Duff</a>. My surname, as well as being the favourite 
        beverage of a bloke called Homer, is derived from the 
        Gaelic <i>dubh</i>, meaning black. It seemed like as good a name
        as any for a web site and no-one else was using it, so here we are...
      </p>
      <p>
        I've been creating web pages since some time in 1994. I'm slowly
        improving after my early fascination with the novelties of black 
        backgrounds, blink tags, marquees and animated gifs some time back
        in early '96 ;).
      </p>
  
    <h2>Hardware</h2>

      <p>
        Dubh.Org runs on a Cobalt RAQ3 dedicated server with a T1 connection
        running Cobalt's
        slightly modified version of Red Hat Linux.  I'm
        renting the server from <a href="http://www.powerraq.com">UK2NET</a>.
        I heartily recommend UK2. They pretty much provide no support unless
        something goes wrong (in which case, they will quickly respond with
        no problems). But this is reflected in the price, which is very, very
        good. Besides, there's a fantastic user community (see
        <a href="http://www.uk2raq.com">uk2raq.com</a> built up around 
        their services).
      </p>
      <p>
        I divide development of this site at home between my main PC
        (a 1GHz PIII Dell Dimension 4100 with 512Mb) and my slightly punier
        650MHz PIII Dell Inspiron 7500 laptop. Again, 
        <a href="http://www.dell.com">Dell</a> did a 
        great job with both computers.
      </p>
      <p>
        My home PC is connected to the internet via a Terayon Cable Modem
        with a fast 512Kbps connection provided by <a href="http://www.ntl.com">
        NTL</a>. Who I pretty much don't recommend, as anyone who has ever 
        had to phone them will understand. See 
        <a href="http://www.frankw.net/network/nthw/">NT<i>Hell</i> World</a>,
        a site dedicated to people who have a gripe with the cable provider :)
      </p>

  
  <h2>Software</h2>

      <p>
        I use the tools in the <b>Oracle XDK</b>
        to dynamically transform <b>XML</b> documents on the
        server. This technology lets me just define the content for each
        page in XML, and dynamically build up all the other stuff (heading, 
        footer, navigator etc.), the layout and the style.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        One of the XDK components, The <b>XSQL servlet</b> is also used to 
        pull data out of the 
        <b>MySQL</b> database I have on my server in XML format and
        transform it to readable <b>HTML</b>. (I'd use Oracle, but 
        trying to upload it to my server would be immensely time consuming, 
        and MySQL came preinstalled on the RAQ. Then there are the licensing
        issues...).
      </p>        
        
      <p>
        The XSQL Servlet relies on <b>servlets</b> and <b>JDBC</b>, two
        integral components of <b>Java 2 Enterprise Edition</b>. The 
        <b>Tomcat Servlet Engine</b> is a key technology - a cleanly
        implemented, open source servlet engine, which is now the
        reference servlet implementation for Java 2 EE. The 
        <b>Apache Web Server</b> is used to serve static content.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        For the online CVS browser, I'm using the <b>JCVS Servlet</b>. 
        I'm a great believer in <b>SCM</b>, so everything (including all
        the pages and configurations for this web site) is in a
        <b>CVS repository</b> on this server.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Any servlets I develop myself, and any other Java code I write
        for the site is currently developed using 
        <b>Oracle9<i>i</i> JDeveloper </b> (I work on the development team
        at Oracle for this product). You can download a copy of the
        Oracle9<i>i</i> Release Candidate for <b>free</b> from
        <a href="http://otn.oracle.com/products/jdev">the
        Oracle Technical Network (OTN)</a> (free registration
        required).
      </p>
  
    <h2>Standards and Browsers</h2>
      <p>
        Until fairly recently, Microsoft's Internet Explorer browser has
        had the best support for <a href="http://www.w3.org">web standards</a>.
        This has made it difficult to write pages that take advantage of 
        client side scripting, stylesheets, even some newer HTML tags unless
        you specifically targeted that browser, or wrote browser specific
        code in each web page. However,
        with the advent of <a href="http://www.mozilla.org">Mozilla</a> (an
        old, buggy, slow version of which was released as Netscape 6), this
        is becoming less of an issue. Mozilla has even better standards
        support than Internet Explorer.
      </p>
      <p>
        For that reason, I <b>am</b> using javascript and other niceties. 
        My use of this stuff is limited to what is specified in the standards
        listed below:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2000/REC-DOM-Level-2-Core-20001113/">
            Document Object Model (DOM) Level 2
          </a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-CSS2/">
            Cascading Stylesheets (CSS), Level 2
          </a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/">
            Hypertext Markup Language (HTML) 4.01 Transitional
          </a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="http://www.ecma.ch/ecma1/STAND/ECMA-262.HTM">
            ECMAScript</a> (of which JavaScript and JScript are implementations)
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-png.html">
            PNG 1.0</a> (incidentally, Internet Explorer on Windows has a 
            shockingly poor level of support for this standard. Mozilla is far better)
        </li>
      </ul>

      <p>
        I test most of my pages on recent Mozilla builds and
        Internet Explorer 6. If other browsers don't display my pages
        correctly, it's likely to be a bug in the browser rather than a bug
        in these pages. Particularly if you're using obsolete browser versions,
        I'd recommend upgrading to the newest versions.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        If you encounter a problem viewing my pages which you feel has been
        caused by me not using these standards correctly, 
        <a href="mailto:Brian.Duff@oracle.com">mail me</a>.
      </p>

  
  <h2>Hosted Sites</h2>

      <p>
        I'm hosting a few other sites on this server. I'm happy to do this
        for people I can trust who need more space for web pages or want to
        play with neato technologies on their pages.
      </p>
      <p>
        <b><a href="http://www.betterbites.co.uk">Better Bites</a></b> is
        the sandwich shop owned by my parents. I wrote a wee web page for them.
      </p>
      <p>
        <b><a href="http://www.leapingfrogs.com">Leaping Frogs</a></b> is
        a site owned by a mate of mine from University.
      </p>
      </html>
  </content>
  
  <cvs-info>
    <date>
      $Date: 2001-12-17 02:55:28 $
    </date>
    <author>
      $Author: briand $
    </author>
    <revision>
      $Revision: 1.6 $
    </revision>
  </cvs-info> 
  
</dubhpage>
