<?xml version="1.0"?>


<sectionedpage>

  <section id="top" name="What is Dubh.Org?">
    <html>
      <p>
        Dubh.Org is a web server which is mostly dedicated to
        the development and support of several open source <a
        href="../projects/index.xml">projects</a> that are hosted on
        this site.
      </p>
      <p>
        The server is maintained by <a href="../brian/index.xml">
        Brian Duff</a>. My surname, which has some unfortunate meanings
        in Northern English slang, as well as being the drink particularly
        favoured by Homer Simpson &amp; chums is actually derived from the Gaelic
        Dubh, meaning black. It seemed like a pretty cool name for a web
        site and no-one else was using it, so I grabbed as many domains
        involving dubh as possible...
      </p>
      <p>
        This site is a highly evolved version of my homepage, which has been
        around on the web since about 1994. 
      </p>
    </html>
  </section>
  
  <section id="hardware" name="Hardware">
    <html>
      <p>
        Dubh.Org runs on a Cobalt RAQ3 dedicated server running Linux. It
        has about 64Mb of memory and a pretty large hard disk. I'm actually
        renting the server from <a href="http://www.uk2net.com">UK2NET.com</a>,
        whom I heartily recommend if, like me, you want to use up to date 
        technologies like servlets and xml, but your ISP doesn't allow this
        kind of thing on their web servers.
      </p>
      <p>
        I mostly develop the site on my Dell Inspiron 7500 laptop at home. Again,
        I'd recommend <a href="http://www.dell.com">Dell</a> to anyone, my 
        experiences with the laptop have been nothing but joyous (yes, I'm a sad
        git).
      </p>
    </html>
  </section>
  
  <section id="software" name="Software">
    <html>
      <p>
        <i>Evil Grin...</i> As much as humanly possible, this site is written
        using XML. I'm using <a href="http://xml.apache.org">Apache Cocoon</a> as
        a web development framework, which allows me write content in XML which
        is rendered to HTML using XML Transformations (XSLT). 
      </p>
      <p>
        Cocoon uses the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org">Tomcat</a> servlet
        engine to work. Both these technologies are written in <a 
        href="http://java.sun.com">Java</a>, which is very quickly becoming <i>
        the</i> language for server side development.
      </p>
      <p>
        I'm also making use of the XSP technology that comes as part of Cocoon.
        This works a bit like ASP or JSP, allowing you to embed server logic
        in your HTML code. However, XSP is completely XML based, and results in
        much cleaner code as a result.
      </p>
      <p>
        All of this may seem like overkill, but it's not. Honest. These
        technologies allow you to separate content from presentation. Anyone
        who has developed a web page knows how much of a pain it can be to 
        preserve the content and change the appearance or style of a page. I
        can do this really easily by modifying the transforming stylesheets; the
        XML files that contain the content of the site don't even have to be
        modified. Likewise, if I need to add or modify content, I don't need
        to plough through large amounts of formatting code to get to the Real
        Stuff.
      </p>
    </html>
  </section>
  
  <section id="othersites" name="Hosted Sites">
    <html>
      <p>
        I'm hosting a few other sites on this server. I'm happy to do this
        for people I know who need more space for web pages or want to
        play with neato technologies on their pages.
      </p>
      <p>
        <b><a href="http://www.betterbites.co.uk">Better Bites</a></b> is
        the sandwich shop owned by my parents. I wrote a wee web page for them.
      </p>
      <p>
        <b><a href="http://www.leapingfrogs.com">Leaping Frogs</a></b> is
        a site owned by a mate of mine from University.
      </p>
    </html>
  </section>

</sectionedpage>
