<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/xsl/sectionedpage.xsl" ?>

<sectionedpage>

  <section id="top" name="What is Dubh.Org?">
    <html>
      <p>
        Dubh.Org is a web server which is mostly dedicated to
        the development and support of several open source <a
        href="../projects/index.xml">projects</a> and other assorted
        technologies I feel like experimenting with on any given day.
      </p>
      <p>
        The server is maintained by <a href="../brian/index.xml">
        Brian Duff</a>. My surname, as well as being the drink particularly
        favoured by Homer Simpson &amp; chums is actually derived from the 
        Gaelic <i>dubh</i>, meaning black. It seemed like as good a name
        as any for a web site and no-one else was using it, so here we are...
      </p>
      <p>
        This site is an "evolved" version of my homepage, which has been
        around since the glorious early web days of mid 1994. 
      </p>
    </html>
  </section>
  
  <section id="hardware" name="Hardware">
    <html>
      <p>
        Dubh.Org runs on a Cobalt RAQ3 dedicated server with a T1 connection
        running Cobalt's
        slightly modified version of Red Hat Linux.  I'm
        renting the server from <a href="http://www.powerraq.com">UK2NET</a>,
        whom I heartily recommend if, like me, you want to mess about with
        up to date technologies like servlets and xml, but your ISP doesn't
        allow this kind of thing on their web servers.
      </p>
      <p>
        I divide development of this site at home between my main PC
        (a 1GHz PIII Dell Dimension 4100 with 256Mb) and my slightly punier
        650MHz PIII Dell Inspiron 7500 laptop. OK, So I'm showing off. These
        numbers won't be so impressive in about a years time when I next edit
        this page :). Again, <a href="http://www.dell.com">Dell</a> did a 
        great job with both computers.
      </p>
    </html>
  </section>
  
  <section id="software" name="Software">
    <html>
      <p>
        I use the <b>Oracle XSQL Servlet</b>,  <b>Oracle XSLT
        Transformer</b> and <b>Oracle XML Parser</b>
        to dynamically transform <b>XML</b> documents on the
        server. This technology lets me just define the content for each
        page in XML, and dynamically build up all the other stuff (heading, 
        footer, navigator etc.), the layout and the style.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        The XSQL servlet is also used to pull data out of the 
        <b>MySQL</b> database I have on my server in XML format and
        transform it to readable <b>HTML</b>. (I'd use Oracle, but 
        trying to upload it to my server would be immensely time consuming, 
        and MySQL came preinstalled on the RAQ. Then there are the licensing
        issues...). 
      </p>        
        
      <p>
        The XSQL Servlet relies on <b>servlets</b> and <b>JDBC</b>, two
        integral components of <b>Java 2 Enterprise Edition</b>. The 
        <b>Tomcat Servlet Engine</b> is a key technology - a cleanly
        implemented, open source servlet engine, which is now the
        reference servlet implementation for Java 2 EE. The 
        <b>Apache Web Server</b> is used to serve static content.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        For the online CVS browser, I'm using the <b>JCVS Servlet</b>. 
        I'm a great believer in <b>SCM</b>, so everything (including all
        the pages and configurations for this web site) is in a
        <b>CVS repository</b> on this server.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Any servlets I develop myself, and any other Java code I write
        for the site is currently developed using 
        <b>Oracle JDeveloper 9i</b> (I work on the development team
        at Oracle for this product). In a few weeks time, I'll probably
        switch over to the first internal alpha of <b>JDeveloper 9i</b>, 
        the new all-Java IDE that's under development at Oracle.
      </p>
     
    </html>
  </section>
  
  <section id="othersites" name="Hosted Sites">
    <html>
      <p>
        I'm hosting a few other sites on this server. I'm happy to do this
        for people I can trust who need more space for web pages or want to
        play with neato technologies on their pages.
      </p>
      <p>
        <b><a href="http://www.betterbites.co.uk">Better Bites</a></b> is
        the sandwich shop owned by my parents. I wrote a wee web page for them.
      </p>
      <p>
        <b><a href="http://www.leapingfrogs.com">Leaping Frogs</a></b> is
        a site owned by a mate of mine from University.
      </p>
    </html>
  </section>

  <cvs-info>
    <date>
      $Date: 2001-04-16 02:53:15 $
    </date>
    <author>
      $Author: briand $
    </author>
    <revision>
      $Revision: 1.3 $
    </revision>
  </cvs-info> 

</sectionedpage>
