<?xml version="1.0"?>


<sectionedpage>

  <section id="whatdju" name="What is DJU">
    <html>
      <p>
        <b>DJU</b> are the <i>Dubh Java Utilities</i>. While writing
        <a href="../newsagent/index.xml">NewsAgent</a>, I realised that
        vast amounts of code could potentially be usable by other projects.
        To this end, I tried to keep common code separate from the rest
        of NewsAgent by putting it in the dju package space. The
        Dubh Java Utilities are the end result.
      </p>
    </html>
  </section>
  <section id="using" name="Using the DJU">
    <html>
      <p>
        You are welcome to use the DJU in your own projects. You simply
        need to download the DJU jar file and make sure it's in the 
        CLASSPATH of your java runtime. Before you do this, you should
        look at the license for DJU to make sure you are complying with
        its terms. More information on the license for DJU is available
        below.
      </p>
    </html>
  </section>
  <section id="licensing" name="DJU Licensing">
    <html>
      <p>
        DJU has not yet been formally released as a separate product. The
        only release so far has been as part of NewsAgent 1.0 and 1.02.
        Both these releases were licenced under the GNU General Public
        License, and no licensing information was available separately
        for DJU.
      </p>
      <p>
        GNU GPL doesn't work very well for libraries of common code like
        DJU. There is a separate GNU license for library code, called the
        LGPL (Library or Lesser General Public License). However, Richard
        Stallman seems to be recommending that even libraries use GPL these
        days.
      </p>
      <p>
        An unfortunate consequence of using the GPL is that, even though it
        is an open source license (and therefore fundamentally less 
        restrictive than most commercial software licenses), it nevertheless
        places a restriction on using the licensed software in what it calls
        "derived products". Derived products must also carry the GPL license, 
        which in effect, makes GPL viral - if you want to use a library licensed
        under GPL in your software, you have to license your software under
        GPL. 
      </p>
      <p>
        This to me seems far too restrictive, and could potentially limit
        the use of the DJU library. For that reason, I'm still considering
        possible licenses for DJU. My current favourite is the MPL 
        (Mozilla Public License), as used by the <a href="http://www.mozilla.org">
        Mozilla</a> project.
      </p>
    </html>
  </section>


</sectionedpage>
